Vinay Kumar

vinay7724@gmail.com

+91-8007081188

Profile:

Working in middleware integration throughout the experience of 10+ years. Worked on tools and technologies like IBM WebSphere Process Server (BPM IID), IBM DataPower and IBM Integration Bus (ACE/IIB/ESB) for orchestration, business integration, process management and security. Used JAVA to automate, innovate and support projects for multiple tasks during the whole experience. Worked on microservices development using spring boot. Learning the latest tools and technologies like Kafka, Jenkins, etc. and cloud technologies like docker, Kubernetes, AWS, etc to upgrade skill sets and sustain in the growing industry.

Key Skill Sets:

Technologies: IBM BPM(IID), IBM Integration Bus (IIB), IBM ACE, Java, Spring Boot

Architecture: SOA, Microservices

Development Tools: IBM Integration Developer 7.0(WID)/ IID 8.5/IID 8.5.7, IBM Data Power,

IIB9/IIB10, IBM ACE 11/12, IntelliJ

Data Base: DB2, SQL, NoSQL(CloudantDB)

Code Repositories: Clear case remote client, RTC, GitHub

Domain: Banking & Finance, Insurance, Child Support, Infrastructure & Capacity management

Other Skills: SOAP web service, REST service, Docker, GitHub, Apache Kafka

Development Methodologies: SDLC(Waterfall), Agile (Scrum)

Key Courses, Trainings and Certifications:

| or an every reasonable areas every e | | |
|--|--|---|
| 1. | Apache Kafka with spring boot – Full Day Training | 5 th April – 9 th April 2021 |
| 2. | IBM Certified Solution Developer Integration Bus v10.0 | 30th June 2020 |
| 3. | Docker Essentials: A Developer Introduction Badge | 5th Jan 2020 |
| 4. | Capabilities Fundamentals (CCF) Training | 12th Oct 2018 |
| 5. | Certified Scrum Master (CSM) | 27th May 2018 |
| 6. | IBM Agile Explorer Badge | 15th Sept 2018 |
| 7. | Banking Industry Foundations Badge | 26th June 2018 |
| 8. | Enterprise Design Thinking Practitioner Badge | 4th Oct 2016 |
| 9. | IBM Certified Integration Developer WPS v7.0 (WID) | 2013 |
| 10. | Microsoft Programming in HTML5 with JavaScript and CSS3 | 22nd March 2013 |
| 11. | Microsoft SQL Server 2008, Database Development | 27th March 2013 |
| 12. | Oracle Certified Professional, Java SE 6 Programmer (SCJP 6.0) | 9th Dec 2010 |

Education Qualifications:

B.Tech. in Information Technology: -Galgotia's College of Engineering and Technology, UP, India, Passed in 2011.

Career History

Total Experience: 10+ years

11/09/2015 - To date (6+ years) IBM India Pvt Ltd, India Working as a Senior Application Developer/Client Facing Role:

Role and Responsibilities:

Worked on a project as bpm application developer to build processes in IBM IID 8.5.6. Worked as a BPM team lead to build and deliver processes in multiple releases. Leading and guiding build team to deliver high quality code.

Worked as an IIB10/ACE12(ESB) application developer to build REST full services and supported testing phases in the same projects. Working with SME to migrate IIB services onto ACE12 platform for cloud deployment.

All experience is in the integration layer for the same banking client in IBM. Worked two years at a client location in the **United Kingdom**. Driving team from onshore to build and deliver services.

Worked as a Spring boot developer to build Rest full services and supported the deployment to cloud using Jenkins's pipeline. All configuration required from build to deployment via pipeline has been done after service developed and unit tested. Unit test with Junit and Ready API testing tools.

Other than deliveries, worked on multiple assets to support development and unit testing. These apps benefit clients in terms of time saving in development and unit testing.

- 1. **BLUApp**: This application helped to update BPM libraries and reduced effort from a day to few minutes. Developed in JAVA. This saved project's 10-15 days of effort and help client to save around 3k pound per delivery. Received **IBM Excellence award** for this app.
- 2. **Test Framework API**: Worked on designing and development of an innovative test framework API, which was built to automate unit testing. This API helps in automation of unit testing for BPM (STPO and LRPO), IIB/ACE, and java spring boot microservices. This is built in JAVA. This framework integrated with SOAPUI and Ready API for unit testing automation. This is now integrated with Jenkins to test a service during CI/CD pipeline and generate the report. Client has accepted this as a great framework so using it in all the projects from last two years. Rewarded with an award from client.

25/08/2014 – 09/09/2015(1 year) Accenture Services Private Limited, India Application Developer

Role and Responsibilities:

Worked as an application developer to integrate between the UI of a portal with web service or business processes. Worked on IBM Data Power tool to implement Authorization and Authentication while integrate the systems. Using XSLT transformations to receive requests and hit backend web services based on SOAP/ REST services. Worked with a team to develop the web services and integrate them with UI portal. Worked with Technical lead and Architect to set and review overall

quality of deliverables. Responsible for developing new services, supporting test phases, and proofing the services to develop required changes to assure production of quality application.

22/08/2011 – 22/08/2014(3 years) Infosys Limited, India System Engineer

Role and Responsibilities:

Creating and converting design to the technical implementation by following standards on programming and documentation. Working with Technical lead and Architect to set and review overall quality of deliverables. Mentoring the peers with the tools and technologies. Creating business processes and integrating SCA components to implement the complete logic. Creating user interactive applications for searching & fetching data from tables & displaying them in excel reports & generating pdfs. Unit and integration testing of all the modules developed. Integrating database, web services interaction with the code. Automating various daily production tasks to minimize daily resource efforts. Handling production tickets and ad hoc requests Creating documentation for various processes followed frequently in the project Created batch jobs using java to send mails automatically which contains details of activity going on and its status. Automated most of the manual tasks using Java Spring framework.

Assignment History In IBM:

Working with the same client since joining IBM and involved in multiple deliveries with different teams and worked on different technologies like BPM, IIB/ACE, Java, Spring boot.

07/2021 - Till Now (8 months) ACE Migration project:

Project Description: Migrating existing IBM IIB10 services onto IBM ACE 12 cloud ready service.

Position: Lead IIB/ACE developer/Designer

Contribution: Worked as an ACE developer to migrate services from IIB10 to ACE12 platform and make them cloud ready and get it deployed on to AWS cloud via Jenkins's pipeline. These are the REST/SOAP microservices that were built in IIB10 and now migrating them to ACE 12 platform. Used SOAPUI with Test Framework API and JUnit test cases to perform unit testing. Also worked as a designer to migrate old design documents onto confluence pages with additional changes required to make services ready for cloud.

03/2021 - 06/2021 (3 months) Java Microservices Migration:

Project Description: Migrating existing IIB services into microservice using Spring Boot.

Position: Spring boot developer

Contribution: Worked as a java developer to develop microservices using spring boot. These are the REST microservices that were built in IIB and now migrating them to java microservices. These services consume multiple SORs to get the data and transform data before responding. Used Ready API with Test Framework API and JUnit test cases to perform unit testing.

03/2020 - 03/2021 (12 months) Multiple Deliveries and projects:

Project Description: Worked in multiple deliveries since March 2020. Mostly worked in bpm development. Worked on a test framework to enhance it and added more features. Worked on production problem records, from providing solutions to design and till fixing services.

Position: Lead bpm developer/Designer

Contribution: Lead BPM team to build and deliver high quality processes. Working as designer to provide solutions of production problem records and did design changes. Also did build changes and provided support to the system test team for any kind of issues. Worked on test framework API by adding new features to it. Successfully delivered two large releases and one small release.

01/2019 – 02/2020 (11 months) Open Banking Project:

Project Description: This project enables clients to provide APIs so that third parties can consume banking services in their applications directly. This is a new feature in UK banking and banks provide their service and APIs to third party applications.

Position: ESB developer/Team Lead/Designer

Contribution: Worked as a senior developer to build and supported IIB10 services during testing phases at client location. Worked closely with the build manager and client to deliver services in multiple releases. Supported path to live activity, which was a complex process to deploy multiple projects at same time in the production. Worked in an agile way to follow scrums and other features of it. Worked as designer to provide solutions of production problem records and did design changes.

11/2017 – 12/2018(11 months) Everyday Banking Project:

Project Description: This project enables the bank to offer customers current account opening without visiting any branch. It uses most of the existing services with some new. Did enhancements of the existing services.

Position: Senior application developer

Contribution: Worked as a developer of IIB and build services. Build and support multiple services up to path to live. Updated build manager on daily bases about the development progress and discussions on issues to short them. Supported system test and system integration test to analyse and fix defects.

04/2017 - 11/2017 (8 months) Enterprise Management Project:

Project Description: This program was an enhancement of the Strategic Origination program. It enables multiple channels to integrate with middleware solutions and starts traffic for multiple channels.

Position: BPM Team Lead/scenario application developer

Contribution: Lead BPM team to build and deliver high quality processes. Coordinated with the design team to get team's queries resolved in less time and help the team to understand the changes. Worked with BPM SME to define coding standards and helped the team to implement them. Daily call with the team to get the development status and help them to resolve issues they faced during development. Updated build manager on daily bases about the development progress and discussions on issues to short them. Supported system test and system integration test to analyse and fix defects. Coordinated with test teams to get issue details and help the team to get it resolved quickly. Supported warranty for release went live in production.

09/2015 - 03/2016 (19 months) Strategic Origination:

Project Description: This program was the first and most critical online saving account opening origination process for clients. This was the first middleware BPM integration project for a client. Everything was built from scratch, from development to deployment scripts to production environment setup. This feature enables customers to open a SA in just 15mins from home and no need to go to the branch.

Position: Application Developer: Process Integration Developer (BPM)

Contribution: My role was to analyse and understand the function specification given by the design team and convert them into services in BPM to enable orchestration in the middleware layer. Moved onshore at client location to support system integration testing and production warranty.

- * Understand function specification, raise queries if any and discuss with the design team.
- * As my role was to create an application to integrate and orchestrate with multiple platforms, I did work closely with ESB/IIB and ODM teams.
- * Whenever a testing team raises queries or wants to clear the function understanding I always help them.
- * Supporting testing teams in different environments to quickly analyse and fix defects if required.
- *Always gave technical KT to team members onboarded the project.

Assignment History in Accenture:

05/2015 - 09/2015 (5 months) Internal Project (R&D) Service Integration:

Project Description: It was the internal project that came under the infrastructure domain. Service integration team providing multiple solutions related to remedy and infrastructure for our clients. Project mainly focused on the providing integration layer between client and its vendors Service Now. Implemented use cases using integration layer to provide solutions and provided solutions in SRM, Configuration, Capacity, Incident and Change management.

Contribution: Worked as a JAVA developer to integrate the BMC remedy ITSM with Service now using soap web services. Worked on BMC Atrium Orchestrator tool to automate and integrate the system. Worked on a use case called intelligent infra automation-1 to automate a process of predicting the issue before its cases affect using predictive analytics tools like BMC ITDA. Worked in a 15 member's team to provide solutions like enabling the information exchange for Incident and Change request between Service now, BMC ITSM and HPSM. Worked with Technical lead and Architect to set and review overall quality of deliverable. Responsible for developing simulators using JAVA to provide the environment that causes issues so that our solution can predict the issue in advance and provides the automated solutions that fix it before it occurs. Participated in providing demos of developed use cases to the higher management and clients.

09/2014 - 04/2015 (8 months) US Based Client: Child Health Care & Support Project:

Project Description: It's a portal used by Texas Govt. for supporting child health care. Present System is in mainframe technology, which was developed around 10 years back. Project is to

redevelop a portal for Texas child health care & support from scratch. Build the process with the latest tools and technology. Total offshore strength is around 120.

Contribution: Worked as an application developer to integrate the UI of a portal with web services or business processes. Worked on IBM Data Power tool to integrate the system. Using XSLT transformations to convert protocols and invoke web services based on SOAP/REST. Worked in 6 member's team to develop the web services and integrate them with the portal. Worked with Technical lead and Architect to set and review overall quality of deliverable. Responsible for developing new services and proofing the services to develop required changes to assure production of quality application.

Assignment History in Infosys:

01/2012 - 08/2014 (32 months): US Insurance Provider - Integration Project

Description: Client works in cooperation with a Pharmacy company, both organizations operating on different platforms. This was a project that implemented various business processes using SOA and EAI concepts to build a new repository to combine pharmacy adjudicated claims data for our client. This project addresses the need to load the new repository to store and support the need for only pharmacy adjudicated claims data with claims adjudicated by one business process system. This repository will need to contain current and historical data. This project comprises many tracks like Member (details of related members), Plan (details of various plans listed out by the insurance organization), Claims (details if claims processed), Rebate (details of claim related rebates), reporting solutions. Worked on this project for around 3 years. Contribution: Responsibilities:

Created and converted design to the technical implementation by following standards of projects programming and documentation. Worked with Technical lead and Architect to set and review overall quality of deliverables. Mentoring the peers with the tools and technologies. Creating business processes and integrating SCA components to implement the complete logic. Creating user interactive applications for searching & fetching data from tables & displaying them in excel reports & generating pdfs. Unit and integration testing of all the modules developed. Integrating database, web services interaction with the code. Automating various daily production tasks to minimize daily resource efforts. Handling production tickets and ad hoc requests Creating documentation for various processes followed frequently in the project Creating batch jobs using java to send mails automatically which contains details of activity going on and its status.

Knowledge transfer and application documentation:

Played a vital role in new team members ramp up and knowledge transfer activities. Drafted help documents for the application operations teams. Drafted help documents on domain knowledge and technologies used in the application for internal use.

08/2011 - 12/2011 (5 months): Infosys Fresher Training

Description: Completed 2 months training on basics of JAVA, DBMS, SQL. Completed 2 months training on advanced JAVA including JSF framework. Contribution: Successfully Completed 4 months of training with 4.82 cgpa out of 5. Completed a project based on JSF framework.